if I want my glutes to get bigger do I
need to be having bands do I should I
not use them like give me that whole
picture of saying okay Brett I want my
butt bigger do all I have to do is hip
thrust do I need to add anything else
what are ad doctors complete that whole
picture about what am I looking at
Anatomy wise and then what implications
do I have for training first of all the
glute Max has upper and lower
subdivisions and some people we been say
there's the you know the iliac fibers
the sacral fibers the coxial fibers
yep they might even separate the glute
Max between three
subdivisions but definitely up and lower
and then the glut has multiple subdiv
and the glut to Maxim development them
you're going to do combine a lot of
different actions there's two studies
one looking at the glute glute size of
Olympic
weightlifters and it shows that their
glute Max is larger than control sub
than sedentary subjects but their glut
me and Min are not meaning squats do not
grow your glut me and Min also the
Plotkin study showed that squats and hip
thrust neither one of them grew your
glut medus and Minimus if you want to
grow your glut and Min you should treat
it like any other muscle and specificity
train it dynamically through a full
range of motion and there's uh one guy
this Chasm pointed out that we're all
doing ab Junction straight out to the
side yep you really should look at the
pelvic shape and kind of go in the plane
of the glute medius which is diagonal at
30° if you look at how the pelvis is
shaped and how the glute medius you
should kick out the problem is it's
really hard for people to get that right
yeah you have a nice way of showing it
in a in like an educ instructional video
you look overhead and you tell them turn
this foot in and then drive back but
it's really hard people they end up
bending over Y and then they're
involving in the glute Max more so it's
it's really hard and then do their foot
go in front or in back and then they end
up at so I have ways of teaching it but
basically for sometimes when it gets
when people keep screwing up like just
go straight out to the side yeah and and
and so but but because the glut me and
men have multiple subdivisions you
probably should do different angles of
abduction yeah um you should go straight
out to the side you should go at a 30
degree angle back you should also do
maybe seated hip abduction straight up
MH uh might develop the poster heads
more but also on the seated hip Abdu
machine Bridge up do them bridged and do
them leaning forward cuz leaning forward
for the glute Max bridged up you could
put blocks like yoga blocks underneath
you or just maintain the bridge position
for the glute me okay what about glute
Max you're going to get the most bang
for your buck with hip
extension um hip extens exercises take
them through the most range of motion
but now you start talking about how to
put the mo together the most
comprehensive program I know in 10 years
especially if I team up with you and we
start doing studies using this MRI stuff
but God that we have a lot of questions
that remain so right now my optimal
program you know the scientific studies
we have to guide us are few yeah we've
got you know Kubo from 2019 showing
deeper squats are better than shallow
squats but that for glute ma GL Max
growth but that just looked at knee
angle they were probably hinging over
and yeah they were Pro no the beginners
doing this sh were probably staying
vertical and we don't have a study
looking at super deep squads versus
parallel I think parallel would either
be more effective or same I don't think
you need to go past parallel for glute
growth there's two studies on quads
showing you deeper is not necessary uh
that Kubo study showed the same quad
growth but it showed greater adductor
and glute growth going deep and then we
so that's this the study that people
cling to about um glutes being worked
more in the stretch there's also an
unpublished study that should I I don't
know why it's not published yet but ma
uh SE Kickbacks grow more glute in the
stretch position but it's a straight leg
Kickback kind of weird um who does
straight leg Kickbacks uh you're not
stretching it the most you're not and
they and they only went to neutral they
didn't go into hip hyper extension so
that doesn't have a lot of ecological
validity with like how we do things in
the field so the best anyone who's
scientific right now who trains people
in real life and works with people and
then also tries to incorporate the
science all right this is what a
reasonably because you get these crazy
in every aspect of social like every
field every there's these politics you
look at anything even in your world more
the physiology and performance World
you'll get these coaches saying this way
and this way you'll get people saying
just train glutes in the stretch
position every muscle grows best from
the stretch position but that's a
fascinating area I have every study on
it categorized into the folders We The
Verdict is not out on every exercise and
depends how if you're a beginner or
trained and how long is long enough but
what that what that whole category of
research has not looked at is com
combining them into a pro like basically
what you can recover from because it
might be that if you just could do one
set a week what would be the best thing
to do maybe it'd be a set of walking
lunges to failure yeah all right if you
can do two sets now what if you have all
the time in the world and you don't mind
doing whatever it takes well then I
would say train three days a week at
least but what if what if what if you
could do hip thrust every day You'
probably get some people developing
overuse injuries but my point is you
could recover from that would that be
more effective than training long muscle
lengths twice a week yes it wouldn't be
as efficient but or possibly wouldn't be
as efficient but you could recover from
way more what if you don't create any
muscle damage after a while and you just
stimulate hyperd trvy and you can
expedite the rate at which muscle new
muscle is laid down we don't know
there's a lot of these questions we
don't know yet so right now train the
glutes three days a week and follow the
rule of thirds the rule of thirds is
something I came up with to illustrate
this concept when you're doing vertical
exercise those are the most demanding on
the central nervous system well it's
funny because if you seen the research
on that we really don't have a lot of
evidence that it's more demanding on the
central nervous system
yeah I'll hold my tongue but go ahead
yeah I don't we need to we need re
evidence of that cuz people know what it
means my vertical exercise you're
meaning squats things like squat
deadlifts lunges step UPS bulgar squats
skater squats pistol squats good
mornings and all their variations yep
those are the vertical exercises the
horizontal are hip thrust glute Bridges
you know your single leg hip thrust um
your back extensions 45° hypers your
Kickbacks but within those there's this
is what makes it so complicated you can
make ex you can make things more knee
dominant or more hip dominant even
Kickbacks what if you did kneeling
Kickbacks yeah then you almost it's
becomes like a step up so I'm talking
about an upright Kickback you know so um
and then a a back extension off a ghd is
horizontal that's pure horizontal 45 is
halfway between but we call it
horizontal because it works the squeeze
position more than the stretch those
exercises do not beat you up in fact
after you've done them for a while they
don't beat you up much at all they don't
create nearly as much muscle damage so
those can be done more frequent
frequently and with more volume and then
lateral exercises um those are like
penalty-free volume because you never do
too much those are going to work your
more of your glut medius and stuff if
you lean forward yes you're going to
work more glut Max but they don't beat
up we just do you
know two to six sets at the end of a
depending on someone's goals typically
at the end of the workout but if someone
really wants to grow their upper glutes
I might say do start with ABD I mean
think about it if you're really wanting
to grow your upper glutes begin with a
frontal plane abduction movement and
maybe end with one yep so then you do
the rule of thirds you do around so and
then here's another simple simple system
three times a week pick one exercise
from four categories the first category
is your thrust bridge and this could be
in any order the second is your squat
lunge and when I say squat lunge it
means split squat step up single leg leg
press um and then you pick a hinge and
the hinge this is where it's kind of it
could be vertical like an RDL it could
be like a 45 hyper it could be a reverse
hyper but it's more straight leggedy hip
extension and then pick a an abduction
movement the abduction could be frontal
plane it could be horizontal plane
leaning forward uh it could be hip
external rotation still so I call it
abduction like lateral rotary so you do
your vertical your horizontal your
lateral rotary but pick an abduction but
also include an abduction there aren't
that many hip external rotation
exercises we do two of them the cable
cuff where you spin y those are hard to
master they're hard to teach but anyway
when you do that system you will fully
develop your glute Max and glut me and
Min the you because when you do pick one
from each of those four that's how do it
three times a week don't do the same
exercise every time that's boring lots
of variation to make sure if there is an
effect of range of motion if there is an
effect on activ
and it's more fun and that's when when
when I see people be like just do rdls
do you imagine Rd these girls train
three times a week first of all you
can't recover from doing squats and
rdl's three times a week with intensity
with with sufficient effort but also um
yeah it's boring and it's you you better
be throwing in single leg rdls that are
not as taxi on the low back yeah so what
I found is you cannot do too much these
guys that are telling people
here's a here's a science-based glute
workout they don't train women because
I'm telling you most of them train three
days a week they train lower body three
days a week these programs would crush
people would absolutely Crush these
women I get carried away sometimes so I
don't do drop sets anymore I don't do
these crazy burnouts I don't do crazy
super sets I'm not trying I don't even I
even do lower reps now than I used to
cuz we used to get carried away I even
used to do like Sumo deadlifts with the
deadlift bar and touch and go that's
like these girls can I had girls doing
315 yeah back in San Diego Ashley got 19
reps Dominique got 11 reps like cuz
touch and go you can bounce that bar up
you can move everyone's cheering you on
cool you did something good and then
you're sore for like a week a month you
can't duplicate that for a month cuz
you're so beat down and that's what I
mean so maybe it's muscle damage maybe
it's like damage to to fascia to discs
yep something Chris Beardsley pointed
out to me when you do a conventional
deadlift you're doing a concentric lift
right yep but what happens to the
Erectors you line you line up in the
arch yep you go to
pull the hips shoot up a little the back
rounds a little bit you pull it up the
before the bar left the ground the
Erectors went into an e you're
activating it it went into an Ecentric
so that can create more damage more
something about the spine when you
really do squats to failure deadlifts to
failure those beat you UPS so you need a
good mix within those categories within
the the squat lunge category some should
be bilateral some some should be
unilateral some should be more quad
dominant some should be more hip
dominant meaning you can do a high bar
squat with the feet elevated but that's
going to be more quad you you can also
do a low bar vertical Shin box squat
sitting back that's more hip dominant
and then that so you want to have
variety within those with the deadlifts
you want to do sometimes you might do a
conventional Sumo deadlift sometimes an
RDR or stiff leg dead sometimes single
egg variations single egg and even good
mornings you can do good single egg good
mornings off the Smith machine you can
get good at good mornings too people say
they're dangerous but that's because
they don't start off light and work
their way up good morning are good
variations to do but the hinge
variations should mix between deadlift
and good mornings and then also 45s and
reverse hypers and back extensions and
then the abduction should be Blended
between uh frontal and transverse plane
and there's so many abduction movements
there's sideline hip raises extra range
sideline hip my favorite are glut medius
hip thrust and gluten medius Kickbacks
um you can Google those but um but my
but basically then the hip thrust
variations should blend between you
could do double leg you could do single
leg and B stance but mostly double leg
but varum
between barbell Smith machine and plate
loaded devices but
also you're getting plenty of work in
this system you're getting plenty of
stretch position work so with the hip
thrust it doesn't always have to be
emphasizing full range or you can
emphasize the lockout in a few different
ways we do a lot of pauses at the top we
do a lot of bar plus band we connect the
bar to bands makes the lockout even
harder and you can do pulses where
you're just doing the top range of
motion if you only did hip thrust and
that was all you ever did then you
should probably do some bottom bottom
pauses bottom range of mod ways to make
the bottom hard but you get those when
you do the lunges the squats the Ard and
this is the best system I've come up
with it's the most scientific way to
train the glutes as we know right now
any reasonable person would say that um
because if you said to yeah if you said
to like a bro okay if you put two inches
on your glutes in the next few months
yeah you think they train it one day a
week no one would train it one day a
week yeah you train it a few times a
week but you got to recover from it and
you can't get carried away in fact a lot
of times when I train my girls if I have
them do reverse lunges off the Smith
machine or the lever squat the plate
loaded Squat and they do two hard sets
I'm like done sometimes one hard set I'm
like just be done you set a PR I'm like
you're going to be sore from that and
sometimes they're like coach I'm I was
so sore thank God I only did one hard
set that's something no one knows to do
anymore they don't they always just do
three to four sets yeah sometimes one
and two sets is fine as well you got to
be able to recover and if you don't
recover then what happens is this
happens in my gym a lot typically on
Fridays and which sucks is because
Friday if you train Monday Wednesday
Friday you have an extra recovery day so
it'd be nice to be fresh on Friday train
hard because you got two days to recover
so optimally that would be your day to
push hard but sometimes they're like
coach I push myself hard on Monday
Wednesday I beat down so what they do is
they do a short muscle length day or
like a they that's when they film their
their influencer workouts and they I'm
like you didn't even do that workout but
that got the most likes so they do
variety they do their Fufu wimpy
movements that PE that the men arguably
so they get pissed at that's when they
do just a uh some Kickbacks some
abductions some light bands bands and
stuff and then they they do that on
Friday they rest Saturday and Sund and
come back Monday and they crush it yeah
because they did a wimpy workout but
that's Auto regulation that's how they
periodize but ideally you wouldn't they
wouldn't have done too much on Monday
and Wednesday to begin with so that
Friday they could have still crushed it
but that's an art unto its own how to
nail your training so that you don't
have to Deo so much and you don't have
to do radical things but that's
something we that takes a lot of years
to
master if you enjoyed this clip you can
watch the full episode by clicking here
[Music]